Figure out, is this the church I want to commit to?
So, again, that registration is online, available right now.
Question for you right before we get into the Word is,
we've been going through Ephesians,
and Paul's encouragement and his praise is,
blessed be God.
And so I wanted you to turn to one person next to you
that you said hi to,
and share with them one thing
that you've been blessed by this past week.
All right, go ahead and share that,
and we'll get into the Word.
Morning, church.
Good to see all of you this morning. I want to welcome all of you. If we haven't met yet,
my name is Pete. I'm one of the pastors here, and I get to share God's word with us this morning.
If you want to open up your Bibles to Ephesians chapter 1, that's where we're going to be looking
into today. As Bo was mentioning earlier, we're kind of just starting this process of going through
the book of Ephesians. It's been an exciting season for our church as we just get kind of
kicked off with a new ministry year. New life groups have started. A lot of new people are
coming and checking out our church. I do want to welcome those of you who are visiting us today.
Really glad you're here. Hope you get to meet God and see some of what he's doing in our church
family this morning. And I hope all of you already have, as we were just discussing with each other,
just a lot of ways that you are being blessed and growing closer to the Lord. I think one thing I
have to share that really encourages me and has been a blessing to me is just seeing people
actually like really pursuing God. I've been so encouraged by that. And whether that's in like
just after our Sunday celebrations, seeing people stick around a little longer just to pray
and seek God. Even seeing people like praying for each other, ministering to each other,
just here, or even people coming up to receive prayer from our prayer team. And just hearing,
like as I meet up with people, hearing people saying like, yeah, I'm reading this in the scripture
these days, and God's speaking to me this way. It's just been so encouraging to be part of a
spiritual family where it's not just about kind of us living in community together, but us as a
community really seeking God together. So turn to someone next to you real quick and say, it's good
to seek God together? All right. And I think this is just a great way for us to be starting
this year of ministry, and especially as we shared about our annual theme of higher calling
and really wanting to rise above temporary pursuits and live for God's eternal purposes,
just seeing many of us saying, I want a closer relationship with God. And I think as we seek
that closer relationship and fellowship with him, well, other things will come out of that,
like we've been talking about a life of faith or even a life of ministry. That comes out of
the relationship with God that we're living in. And so we're going to really be digging deep into
that, especially here in Ephesians chapter 1, and we'll keep going in that throughout the year.
But I'm excited to get into that this morning, and for us to really dig into and think about
what does it look like to not just know the gospel, but then live in the truth of the gospel
together. And I think that's something that's really powerful, that can really change things
in our lives and in the world around us. And actually to get started, just with kind of a
quick illustration of that. I wonder how many of you here, if you want to, you can raise your hand,
you don't have to, but how many of you are familiar with this historical period called
the Troubles in Northern Ireland? Okay, there's like a couple of you that know what that is. Okay,
it's all right. Some of you, when I describe it, you'll maybe be like, oh, okay, yeah, I've heard
of that before. There's this period in Northern Ireland known as the Troubles, and this started
around the 1960s, and it started with this conflict about what the future of Northern
Ireland would be. And it's something that really kind of took over that whole country for about
30 years, where there was this ongoing conflict. And it was a conflict between two parties,
two groups of people. One of those were the nationalists or the Republicans, who were mostly
Catholic. And these were people who wanted a united Ireland, who wanted Ireland and Northern
Ireland to be in unity together. And the other party were the unionists or the loyalists. These
were mostly Protestant, and these are people who wanted Northern Ireland to remain part of the
United Kingdom. And so there was this whole conflict over this, and it wasn't just like a
political conflict, like politicians shaking their fingers at each other. It erupted into urban
warfare, where paramilitary groups like the Irish Republican Army or the Ulster Volunteer Force,
You know, there were just consistent attacks, car bombings, shootings, all these kinds of
things happening over that 30-year period with different spikes and then like kind of
a lull and then another spike.
But it was a consistent period of violence for three decades.
Over 3,600 people were killed during the Troubles and estimates of between 30,000 and 50,000
additional injuries during that time.
So this was not a small thing.
This was something that really took over this whole nation.
And in that time, neighborhoods became segregated, and they were segregated along those party
lines, where if, you know, people that were part of these different parties wouldn't live
in the same neighborhood with each other, they kind of blocked off these neighborhoods
with what they called peace lines.
But actually, what a peace line meant is if you cross it, there's not going to be any
peace.
Like, you're going to get attacked.
You might get killed if you go into the wrong neighborhood.
So it was an incredibly divisive time in Northern Ireland's history, and political solutions didn't seem to be going anywhere.
Over these decades, politicians tried to solve these problems.
They tried to start negotiations, but anything that they tried just stalled out, collapsed,
because everyone's just so suspicious of each other.
Nobody trusts each other to be true to their word, and so no solutions really went anywhere.
And during these times, I mentioned that one of these parties was predominantly Protestant and the other predominantly Catholic,
It wasn't necessarily a religious conflict, but it was more of a political or a social
conflict, and yet they kind of broke down into those groups.
And so even a lot of the institutional churches, Protestant and Catholic churches, would kind
of buy into that tribalism of their surrounding society and sort of pick sides and kind of
see the others as enemies, and all that kind of stuff was going on as well.
But at the same time, there were believers in Christ in that country who wanted to live differently,
who wanted to see a different solution.
So, for instance, there was one group called the Cori Mila community that actually became a space
where Protestants and Catholics from warring neighborhoods would get together.
They would live, they would eat, they would pray, they would dialogue together
and really find unity through faith in Christ.
And this was a community that started to bring some healing to the nation.
Along with that, many clergy people at that time, on both sides, Catholic and Protestant,
would kind of act behind the scenes to open lines of communication and negotiation between these warring factions.
And so they would talk with opposing politicians, they would talk with these opposing paramilitary groups
and try to kind of bring people together as trusted intermediaries in those conflicts.
So the clergy kind of stepped up to try to play those roles.
And most powerfully, most substantially, there were many followers of Jesus at that time who chose to publicly forgive those who had murdered their family members.
Came out and publicly said that.
And in doing so, became a powerful witness of the gospel to bring reconciliation and restoration of those relationships and in those communities.
And the fruit of these believers living out their faith and demonstrating the gospel in this way led to actually real change in this country.
That culminated specifically in what was called the Good Friday Agreement that was made on April 10th in 1998.
This was kind of a huge turning point in this conflict,
that after 30 years of violence and bitterness and division and hatred,
that finally these parties came together and said,
we're going to make peace and we're going to put an end to this violence.
And there were still some things that happened after that,
but that largely brought about the end of this period known as the Troubles.
Now, I share that today partly because I think it's just a great testimony of the power of
the gospel to bring real change in the lives of people and even in communities.
But at the same time, as we think about that, and I want us to know there is that power,
we also recognize that in a fallen world, these kind of political agreements come and
go.
It doesn't mean that there's no more issues, that it will never flare up again, or that
everything is totally solved.
But today, as we look into our passage in Ephesians 1, we're going to see actually a
greater and more ultimate hope and unity empowered by the gospel message. And we're going to explore
the power of the gospel to deal with the problem of sin in our lives and ultimately unite all
things in Christ. That's what we're going to talk about today. I'm going to go ahead and give you our
one thing as we start out here today. A lot of times I save it at the end, but I'll give it to
you at the beginning. It's to trust God's gracious plan to unite all things in Christ. Trust God's
gracious plan to unite all things in Christ. And we're just taking short passages in Ephesians
as we go through it this year.
So today we're going to go through verses 7 through 10.
I'll go ahead and read this for us.
It says this.
In him we have redemption through his blood,
the forgiveness of our trespasses,
according to the riches of his grace,
which he lavished upon us in all wisdom and insight,
making known to us the mystery of his will,
according to his purpose,
which he set forth in Christ
as a plan for the fullness of time
to unite all things in Christ,
things in heaven and things on earth in him amen let me pray for us as we've read god's word
lord we invite you once again into this time into this spiritual family that you have brought
together and formed for your purposes we invite you here lord because we want to hear from you
we want you to speak to us through your holy word lord to give us hope to give us direction to show
us the power of the gospel message to lead us in living in that gospel truth and power to be
a testimony of your saving grace, Lord, and to live in the joy of that truth together. God, we pray
that you come and do this work in each and every one of us today, God, and in us as a community
together. Lead us in your word and in the life you've called us to, Lord. Lead us into that higher
calling that you have for each one of us. In Jesus' name we pray. Amen. Amen. So as we look into
today's passage, many of you probably remember if you were with us last week, we looked at verses
three through six in Ephesians one, and we heard how the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ
has blessed us in Christ with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly places. And we started
to unpack a little bit what those spiritual blessings were. But we know it's going to go
on through the rest of Ephesians one. We saw some of those spiritual blessings, like being chosen
as holy and blameless children of God that were adopted as God's daughters and sons, as children
of the king. And today, we're going to see more of those blessings unfold and be invited to live
in those together and kind of see the ultimate purpose behind those blessings as well. So as we
start to dig into this passage, what we first want to focus in on are some really powerful words
like redemption, forgiveness, and grace. And these are like pretty common Christian terms. If you hang
out with Christians or in the church long enough, you'll probably hear these words a lot of different
ways. People kind of use them very frequently among Christians. For some of you who may be new
to the church, and I want to welcome you if you are new to the church, if you're new, checking out
the Christian faith, exploring, asking questions, maybe a friend invited you. We're so glad you're
here. We want to make sure everyone's on the same page of what these mean. But also, even for those
of us who are Christians, we may sometimes throw these terms around without really digging in and
knowing what it is that we're saying when we use these terms. And so we want to, all of us, get on
the same page with that here today. And so let's think about redemption and forgiveness to start.
I'll give you just Greek background of these words real quick. The word translated as redemption,
that's apolitrosis. It means to release or set free with the implied analogy to the process of
freeing a slave. So to set free, to liberate, to deliver, to redeem. So this is specifically
talking about buying someone out of slavery. That's what redemption means. That's what it
means to redeem. We're not talking about a general idea. We're not talking about maybe like a football
team trying to redeem themselves or something. We're talking about redeeming out of slavery.
That's what this means. Then if we look at forgiveness, what's that? Where's that come from?
It's a Greek word, aphesis. It means to remove the guilt resulting from wrongdoing. So if somebody
is guilty because of something they've done wrong, aphesis, forgiveness, that means to remove
that guilt somehow. So when we look into this passage and we're trying to understand what it
is talking about, it's talking about that this is what Jesus has done for us. This is what happens
when we are in Christ. And as we look at this here, we're not only seeing what Jesus has done
for us, we also get to see the other side of the coin of what sin actually does in our lives.
And so I want us to dig in there a little bit. As much as it's not fun to talk about sin,
it's important because if we don't talk about the reality of sin, we're not going to really
understand and appreciate what it is that Jesus has done for us. So specifically, if we just take
the flip side of this coin, we can understand in this passage that what sin does is it makes us
guilty and enslaved. That's what sin does. And let's dig into that a little bit. When I say sin
makes us guilty and enslaved, I'm referring to the spiritual effect of sin on our lives.
I also don't want us to forget that we're not merely victims of sin, but we're perpetrators of
sin. Sin is not just something we're victims of, and we're just kind of passively, oh, sin happens
to me. No, we sin. We do things that are against God's will. We rebel against his revealed word,
his command. We do things that offend his honor and glory. We do things that sin against one
another as well. We all do that. The effect of that on our lives is that we become guilty and
enslaved. And so think about this here. Paul, as he's writing this letter to the church in Ephesus,
he's not coming up with these as like new ideas out of nowhere. He, in all of this, he's referring
back to the Old Testament that the Jewish people had known for centuries at this point. And he's
thinking probably about things like Proverbs 5.22. It says, the iniquities of the wicked ensnare him,
and he is held fast in the cords of sin. So he's saying when we fall into sin, we actually
become ensnared by it, trapped by it, unable to get out of it. If I could describe like what that
might actually look like just in a very simple example, like just imagine that a person has
been dishonest about a seemingly small matter. Maybe they told what they thought was a little
white lie to get out of the consequences of something, okay? So maybe like, oh, did you,
you know, maybe something like, did you leave the toilet seat up? No, I didn't do that.
Somebody else must have come along and done that.
Okay, well, it seems like a little white lie
to get out of being in trouble for not putting the toilet seat down.
It seems small.
But now imagine, somebody else comes along and says,
well, no one else has gone in and out of that bathroom.
Maybe now that person's kind of stuck.
Now, okay, I need to come up with another lie
to cover up my previous lie
if I don't want to take responsibility for it.
And so I come up with something of like,
oh, maybe the dog went in there and did it.
And then someone says, oh, but the dog's been outside for the last two hours.
Oh, God.
Maybe the cat did.
I don't know.
Like, you see, people start coming up with lies to maintain lies.
And the further you go down that path,
now significant relationships are on the line.
And a person's reputation in front of others are on the line.
And this becomes a snare wrapped around a person that started with just a small seed of seemingly meaningless dishonesty that now has ensnared that person where now they have to keep that lie going and try to use deception to avoid responsibility and save face.
And that becomes habitual.
It becomes the way we live.
And you can apply that to anything, right?
I'm just using a very small, simple example.
How much more powerful is that snare, that enslavement,
when it deals with things that are of heavier weight
and their impact on our lives and on those around us?
And I want us to realize here as we think about this,
that this starts affecting us in a lot of different ways,
and it ends up damaging the relationship with people around us,
but especially damaging our relationship with God.
That's the biggest deal here.
We tend to think and be more aware of how sin affects relationship with people,
when somebody's offended, when trust is broken, things like that.
But this most deeply affects our relationship with God.
And here again, Paul, he's not coming up with these days out of nowhere.
He's probably thinking way back to the beginning in a creation account.
Go back to Genesis chapter 2 when what does God tell Adam?
It says,
the Lord God commanded the man, saying, you may surely eat of every tree of the garden,
but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil you shall not eat, for in the day that you
eat of it you shall surely die. From the beginning, God said, hey, if you do this thing I'm telling
you not to do, it's not a small matter. It's going to lead to death. And here, really think
about that, like how easily we fall into this and the destruction that brings in our relationship
with God. And like, let me show you this painting real quick. This is my favorite painting of the
Garden of Eden. And I've probably shared it with our church before. It's by Thomas Cole.
And I love this painting because, you know, in most depictions of the Garden of Eden,
what do you see? In most depictions of the Garden of Eden, you see like the tree is right there with
the fruit on it. And Adam and Eve, they're just hanging out there in all their glory, right? And
then there's the serpent. Maybe the serpent is wrapped around the tree or like they're kind of
on the branch of the tree whispering in Eve's ear or something. And it's almost like, oh,
this temptation is just like looming over you and it's like the only thing you can see. But I think
this is much more accurate. Where are Adam and Eve in this? You can't even see him probably from
where you are. They're on the like bottom center left. I don't know if you can maybe see him there.
And it paints the picture much more realistically.
This glorious, beautiful, abundant, fruitful creation
that God made for humanity and placed them in it
where they would have everything they need to live
and all of those created things to enjoy everything that they need.
And God says, hey, just one thing.
Just one thing.
Don't eat the tree.
Don't eat the fruit from the tree way over there.
And yet this is what humanity falls into.
And God says that is going to bring death.
It's important for us to wrestle with these things
because we live in a culture that makes light of sin
as if it kind of doesn't really matter.
And so some of us forget the enormous problem that sin is for us.
It enslaves us.
It covers us in guilt and shame.
It leads to our spiritual death.
We'll talk about more of that in Ephesians chapter 2.
Especially it separates us from God.
And we need to recognize that, like how serious an issue that is
and that we can't rescue ourselves from this.
We can't fix this problem ourselves.
And as we live dealing with this problem of sin
and even in relationship with other people,
we have a strong tendency to magnify the severity of other people's sins
and point our fingers at others
while we tend to kind of minimize
the severity of our own sins
and think they're not such a big deal.
But if even eating a piece of fruit
off a tree is something that offends God
to the point of death,
maybe we should wrestle with this.
Like J.I. Packer writes,
there can be no small sins against a great God.
And so we can't minimize this.
As much as we don't like talking about it,
I don't like talking about sin.
as much as you don't like talking about it we have to wrestle with this to even understand
what it is that christ has done for us and again this is why it's such good news that what we find
out in this passage the first side of the coin that we skipped over for a second is that jesus
forgives and redeems us jesus forgives and redeems us and again paul's not coming up with
new ideas here paul sees in christ the fulfillment of everything that has gone beforehand everything
in the Old Testament that he knows. He's pointing out to us here, number one, it is specifically
through the blood of Jesus that is shed on the cross that secures our forgiveness and our
redemption and our adoption, all of those things. But these are all pointing back toward things that
were first set up in the Old Testament. So for instance, if we go back to the Old Testament
book of Leviticus, that lays out the sacrificial system that was used to atone for sin during that
period of history. To give you like a quick touch point to help us understand what we're talking
about here, like why through the blood of Jesus? Why does the blood of Jesus matter? That seems like
a very strange thing to our ears, right? But understand this the way that it's shown to us
in Leviticus. Leviticus 17.11 says, for the life of the flesh is in the blood, and I have given it
for you on the altar to make atonement for your souls, for it is the blood that makes atonement
by the life. So you look at that, and then you scan through some other chapters, like chapters
1 through 7 and 16 of Leviticus, and you start to realize that in the Bible, blood signifies life
surrendered in death. And blood on the altar represents a life-for-life substitution. That's
what's being presented to us here, that Paul is looking at this through that lens. And so when we
see the blood of Jesus poured out on the cross, now this is a fulfillment of that. And yet it's
not only in the sacrificial system, but even when we look back to the stories of the Old Testament,
like the Passover. Many of you are familiar with this, when God rescued the Hebrew people
out of slavery in Egypt, that God brought judgment on the land of Egypt for holding the Hebrews in
slavery, right? And it was through the blood of a lamb that protected the Israelites from sharing
in the judgment on the Egyptian people. So you're probably familiar with this, but Exodus 12, 21 to
23 says, then Moses called all the elders of Israel and said to them, go and select lambs for
yourselves according to your clans and kill the Passover lamb. Take a bunch of hyssop and dip it
in the blood that is in the basin and touch the lintel and the two doorposts with the blood that
is in the basin. None of you shall go out of the door of his house until the morning for the Lord
will pass through to strike the Egyptians. And when he sees the blood on the lintel and on the two
doorposts, the Lord will pass over the door and will not allow the destroyer to enter your house
to strike you. So when we see these reference points, we start to understand that for the
Israelites, the blood of the sacrifice on the altar atoned for their sins and the blood of the Passover
land redeemed them out of slavery and judgment. And so now when we fast forward here, we realize
what it is that Christ came to do because what happened in the Old Testament and, you know,
these things like sacrifices on the altar or the Passover, these were things the Jewish people did
year after year after year on the day of Yom Kippur, the day of atonement, or at the Passover
festival. They would do these things over and over again saying, God, we need you to atone for our
sins. God, we need you to set us free from slavery and judgment. They would do this over and over
again. But what Christ came to do was to do that one time to solve the problem of sin permanently.
And the author of Hebrews describes to us how this happens. Hebrews 9, 11 to 15,
but when Christ appeared as a high priest of the good things that have come, then through the greater
and more perfect tent, that's referring to the tabernacle, not made with hands, that is not of
this creation, he entered once for all into the holy places, not by the means of the blood of goats
and calves, but by means of his own blood, thus securing an eternal redemption. For if the blood
of goats and bulls and the sprinkling of defiled persons with the ashes of a heifer sanctify for
the purification of the flesh, how much more will the blood of Christ, who through the eternal
Spirit offered himself without blemish to God, purify our conscience from dead works to serve
the living God. Therefore he is the mediator of a new covenant, so that those who are called may
receive the promised eternal inheritance, since a death has occurred that redeems them from the
transgressions committed under the first covenant. So this is what Jesus came to fulfill and to do,
and the author of Hebrews goes on into chapter 10, and he says, for since the law has but a shadow
of the good things to come, instead of the true form of these realities, it can never, by the same
sacrifices that are continually offered every year, make perfect those who draw near. What we take
from this, brothers and sisters, is that Jesus offered one perfect sacrifice for sin that secured
eternal forgiveness and redemption. That now that slate is wiped clean and we can know God. And he
didn't just do this in like a small measure. We find out in this passage he did this according
to the riches of God's grace. According to the riches of God's grace. And we need to understand
this about God's grace. Many people say that God's grace is unmerited favor, unmerited favor from
God, receiving something that we didn't earn, and that's true, but that's actually only like half of
it. Because what the reality is, is it's not just that we didn't deserve the good things that God gave
us, it's that we actually also deserved the bad side of guilt and judgment and slavery to sin that
we were living under. Harry Ironside says this, grace is the very opposite of merit. Grace is not
only undeserved favor, but it is favor shown to the one who has deserved the very opposite.
So while we in our sin had rebelled against God, actually deserved judgment for the sins that we
had committed. Instead, we are given grace. Grace, love, forgiveness, redemption, restoration,
and coming back to God. This is what God's grace secured, and this grace was very expensive.
It came at the price of God's son, Jesus, and it says in verse 8 that he lavished us with this
grace. He lavished it upon us. It wasn't just like a little bit, it was a lot. Like, think about
it this way because in talking here about like according to the riches of God's grace, we need
to understand the difference between somebody giving out of their riches and someone giving
according to their riches. Like maybe I'll put it this way to maybe help us understand a little
bit. Let's just imagine, and some of us maybe this isn't so hard to imagine, imagine that you're
a college student who is struggling financially and you're getting close to graduation and you've
accumulated massive student debt. Let's say it's like $400,000 of high interest student debt, and I
know that's not impossible for some of us here, okay? And maybe for that $400,000 in student
debt, maybe you got a degree that's not going to pay off very well. Okay, let's just imagine that
that might be your reality. And in that reality, let's say you go out and you're sitting on the
diag one day, just enjoying the rays of sunshine and nice fall weather, but sitting there wondering,
what is my future going to hold with all this debt, and I'm not sure what job I'm going to get,
and things just don't look very good. And so you're sitting there on the Diag, and as you're
sitting there, you just happen to see one of the founders of Google walking through campus.
Larry Page walks by, because he's actually a U of M alumni, and so he's walking through campus,
reliving his undergrad years, he's walking through the Diag, you know, and he's, I'm going to step on
that M, you know, he's just going through, doing his thing, right? And as he's walking through,
you just remember, oh, Larry Page is a multi-billionaire. Maybe this guy can help me out a
little bit. So you flag down Larry Page. Hey, Larry. Hey, buddy. You get his attention. You
explain your situation. I'm in all this debt. I don't know where I'm going to get a job. I'm
going to spend my lifetime paying this off. I don't know what I'm going to do. And let's say
Larry hears you and he says, man, that sounds really tough. Let's say he grabs his wallet,
it, pulls it out, pulls out a crisp $100 bill. Here you go, buddy. Here you go, friend. Hope that
helps out a little bit. Larry, in this situation, has just given out of his riches. Doesn't make
much of a difference for him or for you, right? He gave out of his riches. He didn't give according
to his riches. Let's say instead, same situation, Larry says, hey, let me sit down with you for a
second. Tell me what's going on. Tell me about yourself and what you're going through. He hears
you out. He says, hey, I want to help you get started on the right foot. I don't want you to go
through life under this pile of debt. I'm going to pay off that $400,000 debt. I'm going to pay it
off completely tomorrow. It's as good as done. As soon as business opens tomorrow, your debt is paid
off. And not only that, it seems like you might need a place to live. So why don't you come and
move out to Silicon Valley? I have a luxury apartment out there, and you can live there as
long as you want. Just consider it yours for as long as you need. And it sounds like you might
have a tough time getting a job with that degree, but you know what? I can do something about that.
Let me make a call. I'm going to set up a new job for you and give you a really high salary,
great benefits, stock options at Google. You're going to be all set. And I think you said you
don't have a car. Why don't you just borrow my helicopter whenever you need it, like just to
get around, you know, go grocery shopping or whatever. Just go ahead and take the copter.
And he just lays all this out for you, right?
Now here, now Larry has not given out of his riches.
He has given according to his riches.
According to it.
Now he still has more than enough for that.
That probably doesn't make a dent in his riches anyway either, does it?
He could do all of that.
But he has given in a way that is according to the resources that he has available.
I share this with you because we need to understand.
when it says that God gives to us
according to the riches of his grace.
He forgives us and redeems us
and he doesn't just reach into his pocket
and kind of throw some spare change our way.
He gives us according to the riches of his grace,
which again means at the price of his own son
and means we're given this eternal inheritance
that we are now forgiven and redeemed and restored
according to the riches of his grace.
Our record of sin is erased.
We're welcomed into the family of God.
We're adopted daughters and sons of the king.
So when we think about that and realize,
wait a second, if I understand that analogy correctly,
that's how deep my debt of sin was.
That's how deep my guilt was.
I could have tried a lifetime
and never been able to get out of it.
and I couldn't have gotten the positive side either I couldn't have earned that on my own
wait that's the riches of God's grace toward me when we start to realize that it's a humbling
and joyful realization and then as we keep going in this passage we come to recognize that what
God has done for us in Christ isn't only about us ultimately. He does love us as his sons and
daughters. He wants to make us his own. He wants to cancel the record of our debt in sin. He wants
to redeem us out of slavery. He wants to do all of that, but it's not only about you and me.
He has a greater plan for it that he's been working out since we learned last week. He's
been working out since before the beginning of time. And that plan is to unite all things in Christ.
To unite all things in Christ. And partly here, I mean, these things are unfolding for us,
but I want to take a moment to point out, it says here that this is making known to us the mystery.
It's making known to us the mystery. And partly this mystery is actually being laid out and
unfolded before us here. And there are even more places in Ephesians where we see more of the
mystery laid out. But I want to pause on this idea of mystery here for a second. Because I think for
many of us, we really struggle that there are things about our faith in Christ that we do not
understand. And I want to ask us to really wrestle with God about that and come to a place where you
can actually accept some mystery in your relationship with God and your faith in him. Like, let me put
it this way. I've had a great, good number of conversations with Muslims over the years, both
here in the U.S. as well as, like, overseas in Jordan. And one of the things I hear is most
often a question, and a question that many Muslims, if they're genuinely wanting to know
Jesus and understand what Christians believe, many of them will genuinely ask this question.
They'll say, hey, you say you believe in one God, but it looks like you have three gods,
Father, Son, and Spirit. Like, what's up with that? What's with the three gods when you say
you believe in one God thing? Like, I don't understand that. Now, some Muslims will ask
that question more antagonistically, wanting to pick a fight. Some will ask it more just wanting
to understand. And my response to that question is usually along these lines, that I'll say
something like, well, you know, as Christians, we believe in one God who exists eternally in three
persons, Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. We believe this because that's what's revealed to us in the
pages of Scripture, that you see Father, Son, and Spirit all having the character and the acts
of God, all being identified as God, worshipped, acknowledged as God, and yet being revealed as
one God. So we believe in one God eternally existing in three persons. And I'll be honest
with you, there are some things about how that works, what that means, that are kind of mysterious
to me. I don't fully understand it myself, but I believe it because that's what's revealed to me
in the Word of God. What do you think about that? They usually say, well, that still doesn't make
much sense to me? How can three exist in one? That just doesn't make any sense. And rather than
trying to give them some analogy like a three-leaf clover or something like that, I usually respond
and say, well, you know what? Isn't God so much greater than us? And Muslims have a high view of
God. We should too. Isn't God so much greater than us? Isn't he so far beyond our comprehension in
his glory, in his righteousness, his holiness, his majesty? Like, isn't he so much greater than we are?
Well, shouldn't there be some things about a God that great that we can't fully understand?
If we could fully understand him, if we could explain every single thing about him, if we
understood everything about who he is, about what he does, about why he does it, about all of that,
wouldn't that mean that that God is actually less than we are?
If we can fit him in our little brains?
And if they're honest, usually the people I'm talking to will say,
hmm, I see what you're saying.
I see what you're saying.
I share that because I think many of us, we need to wrestle with God,
who he is and his plans in the same kind of way.
I know that's even coming up for some of us right now as we go through Ephesians.
You know, maybe we're a little bit confused about what we talked about today.
How does Jesus' blood forgive our sins?
I'm still not really sure.
Why does that work that way?
I'm not sure if that makes sense to me.
Maybe some of us, that's a little bit mysterious.
As we look at today's passage,
we realize prior generations didn't understand God's plan.
They didn't understand how the Passover
and the sacrifices and the Old Testament laws,
they didn't understand how that worked
and how that pointed to Jesus.
Now we do.
We understand that mystery in a way that they didn't.
For others of us, maybe as we brought up last week,
Maybe there's some mystery in how God's sovereignty
and human responsibility and freedom interact.
I'm not sure how this makes sense.
Not sure what to do with that.
There's some mystery there.
We're gonna talk about in chapter two,
the mystery of how God reconciles
both Jew and Gentile in Christ.
There's more mystery to be unveiled here.
I share all of this because we need to recognize
that we are less than God.
And like 1 Corinthians 13, 12,
another letter written by Paul,
for now we see in a mirror dimly, but then face to face. Now I know in part, then I shall know
fully, even as I have been fully known. We're not going to understand everything right now.
I thank God that Christian faith, the scriptures, they're intellectually consistent, reliable,
trustworthy. I think they make more sense out of the world as a worldview by far than any other
system philosophically or otherwise that there is out there. That's all real, and yet there are
still some things that we're not fully going to understand. I share this again to say there should
be some room in your faith in Christ for some mystery, because if there's some things we're
not going to fully understand, and I would ask us to caution ourselves in a couple ways around
that, because there's a risk that for some of us, we want God to be fully within our understanding,
so we start actually judging and critiquing God when we don't understand things about his will.
And no matter how we try to wrestle with God,
we should not put ourselves in a place of being judged over him,
critiquing him, saying,
God, why don't you just see things the way that I do?
I'm trying to make sense of this for you, God.
I'm doing you a favor.
For some of us, maybe it's we try to rescue God
from ways we think that his plan doesn't make sense.
We think our way is going to be a better way.
I would encourage us to have a humble posture,
even as we study the scriptures,
to say God is revealing himself and his plan
and his will, these mysteries to me,
and some of it, I can understand the way
that people in the past couldn't,
like the Jewish people in the Old Testament,
they couldn't understand this fully.
I can understand this now because it's revealed to me.
There's other stuff I can't fully understand yet,
but one day, I'm not gonna see through a mirror dimly anymore.
I'm gonna fully know, and so I can wrestle with this,
but I can also trust and rest in this.
And I think this is so important
because ultimately God wants us to be able to rest
and trust in him and his word
and what's been revealed to us.
So he's making known to us this mystery.
And here in this passage, the specific mystery
that's being made known is the God's will, purpose, and plan.
He's saying that it's being laid out for you now.
God's telling you directly, this is what it is.
My plan, he says, is being set forth in Christ.
That means that his plan is revealed
in the person and work of Jesus, it's fulfilled in Jesus. This is what's being laid out for you here
so you can fully understand it, and this is a plan for the fullness of time. What does that mean?
That means that before time began, it started. That means when time reaches its fulfillment at
the end of history, it will be finished. That means in the fullness of time, because God sees
all of it, he is going to bring to fulfillment his plans and his purposes, and specifically that
plan and purpose is to unite all things in heaven and earth. To unite all things in heaven and earth.
And that means that his plan is to completely redeem and restore the division between sinful
humanity in a broken creation and God's eternal kingdom of righteousness and peace. That's what
God wants to do. And remember, does this have to do with conflict between people? Like warring
societies, armies fighting each other, politicians screaming at each other, cultures hating each
other. Does it have to do with that? Yes, it does. But where that redemption and reconciliation
happens is not just among those people by themselves on earth. It only happens in relationship
with God through Jesus Christ. That's the only way that it happens. And we see that being
described for us in Revelation, don't we? Revelation 21, 1-5, one of my favorite passages,
then I saw a new heaven and a new earth for the first heaven and the first earth had passed away
and the sea was no more and I saw the holy city new Jerusalem coming down out of heaven from God
prepared as a bride adorned for her husband and I heard a loud voice from the throne saying behold
the dwelling place of God is with man he will dwell with them and they will be his people and
God himself will be with them as their God he will wipe away every tear from their eyes and death
shall be no more, neither shall there be mourning, nor crying, nor pain anymore, for the former things
have passed away. And he who was seated on the throne said, behold, I am making all things new.
This is the hope that we look forward to. God is going to, in his great plan, his will,
his purpose, he is going to unite all things in heaven and earth, bringing everything together
at the throne of Jesus Christ
with everything being made new,
all the stain of sin being wiped away,
nobody enslaved to sin any longer.
That is God's plan and purpose
that he desires for all of us.
And I think every single one of us here right now
can recognize this is definitely not
the way the world is right now.
And in fact, we should be honest
that the world around us,
trying to fix itself,
where there's a lot of good things
people can try to do,
people can try to do great humanitarian work,
great acts of generosity and servant
humanly speaking great things
it's great that people are doing that
but the world is not going to fix itself
apart from Christ
we should be honest with that
and say we actually have a greater hope
a greater solution
a mystery offered to us in the pages of scripture
through God's son Jesus Christ
and really when we look at the world around us
and see that lack of hope
we should also be able to look at ourselves
as Christians
as the church
and realize that maybe we're not living this out right now either.
We aren't yet that bride adorned for her husband.
Why is that?
Because we're not really living in the truth of the gospel
that we're talking about today.
So think about that.
This is a great challenge for us.
This idea of higher calling that we have this year.
Again, there's parts of that higher calling that are about serving God,
taking steps of faith,
stuff like that that I think are beautiful
and wonderful to see,
but it must start in our relationship with God.
Are we living in relationship with God
and then even with other people
in a way that reflects and magnifies
and testifies to God's plan
accomplished through his son, Jesus Christ?
And I think the hard reality of that
is for many of us,
this is not what our lives look like right now.
God is inviting us into that.
And for many of us,
I want us to wrestle with the fact
that this might actually be damaging to our faith
the way we're living right now.
Because while God says you're forgiven and redeemed,
you're purchased out of slavery,
the record of your guilt is wiped clean.
For many of us, that's not how we're living
in relationship with God or with other people.
How do I know that?
How many of us are living right now
and snared in that web of lies and deception?
It's got a hold on us.
We're scared.
If we bring it to the surface, we bring it to God.
If we bring it to other people,
we feel like we're going to be rejected.
How many of us, living condemned by past mistakes,
were scared to death that somebody would find out what we've done before?
And when we live that way,
while we say we believe the gospel of Jesus Christ,
everything in our lives, our relationship with God,
our relationship with others actually testifies the opposite. And this is why today I don't want
to gloss over this. I don't want to gloss over this problem of sin and how this affects us. I want
us to really dig into that and realize God has revealed his plan through Jesus so that we can
join him in that plan. Like that one thing I shared at the beginning, trust God's gracious
plan to unite all things in Christ. But I want us to really wrestle with this. What does this mean
for me? What does this mean for us? How do I not just say I believe in these truths like we recited
the Apostles' Creed earlier, but how do I actually live in this? Myself, with God, and even in
relationship with my brothers and sisters in Christ. So can I give us some things here to
reflect and pray about as we close out our time here this morning? First question I want to ask
us to think through is, how do you deal with the problem of sin in your life? How do you respond
to that? Because all of us have sin. First John says, if anyone claims they don't have sin, he's
a liar and the truth is not in him. All of us have sin. There's not a single one of us who doesn't.
How do we deal with that? How do we deal with that? I think what the world does around us who doesn't
know Christ is hide from sin. Pretend it doesn't exist. Try to justify that sin. Oh, well, here's,
I have this justification for why what I did is actually the right thing to do, even though I
know that it's wrong. Sometimes it's in comparing ourselves with others. Oh, well, yeah, I did this,
but man, that person over there, they're much worse than me.
They did that, so what I did isn't really that bad.
Or even trying to redeem ourselves.
Yeah, maybe I did that bad thing,
but look at all the good things I'm doing.
Look at how kind I am to others.
Look at the ways I serve.
Look at how generous I am.
Maybe even, as we realize,
probably realize for a second,
this isn't just how the world deals with sin,
this is how many of us deal with sin.
Maybe it's even, look how much I'm serving God.
God, look how faithful I am.
in worshiping you. God, look how much more scripture I know than that person next to me.
God, look how many more missions trips I've gone on. God, look how much I sacrifice my time and
energy for you. God, doesn't that cover over these things that I've done? And brothers and
sisters, it's not just that this is like the wrong way to handle it. You don't have to live
under this weight any longer. You don't have to hide. You don't have to pretend. You don't have
to justify yourself. You don't have to compare and compete with others. You don't have to try to
redeem yourself any longer. As the church, as followers of Jesus, we can actually be honest
about our sin and live in freedom and our need for grace because the debt's already been paid by
Jesus Christ. It's already been paid. You don't have to pay for it anymore. You don't have to hide
from it. You don't have to cover it up anymore. You don't have to try to redeem yourself anymore.
The price has already been paid. Can you tell somebody next to you the price has already been
paid. And I want to encourage us, like, learn, like, how do you deal with this problem of sin?
The way that we do that, the way we do that is actually first with God and then with others,
that we bring that to God and say, God, this is the way that I've turned away from you. I'm not
going to hide from it anymore. I'm not going to pretend that it was okay anymore. I'm not going to
justify myself anymore. I'm not going to compare anymore. God, I'm just going to be honest about
my sin, and I'm gonna bring it to you, and I'm gonna trust that Jesus, through that blood shed
on the cross, that blood that redeems, that blood that forgives, that it set me free. The weight can
be lifted from my shoulders. I don't need to hide from you anymore, God, and I don't need to hide
from others either, and then even in relationship with others. We can bring those things into the
light. We can bring it to one another and say, this is how I've sinned. Can I tell you, this is
one of the most important things that I've had to learn. If I could just share personally, very
briefly, I remember I had to learn this lesson the hard way because I, like everybody else, grew up,
this is the way you do it. You hide, you justify, you pretend, you try to avoid it. But I remember
like probably roughly 20 years ago or so, I was here in our church. I've been following Jesus for
a few years, thought I knew the right answers. But I was here, I was serving, I was serving as a leader
in our church. By the way, having a leadership title doesn't mean you're not sinning, just FYI.
and I was serving in leadership, and there was another person serving in leadership,
and I didn't like some of the decisions he was making, ways he was leading, stuff like that,
and I was not in a good place spiritually, I don't think. Again, like, being a leader doesn't mean
you're not struggling spiritually, and out of that, there was just this bitterness in my heart,
this judgment in my heart, and I started, I was just, like, getting really angry at this other
person serving in leadership, and I was, I would, and I knew I shouldn't, like, do anything really
outwardly, but what I would do is, like, I would, you know, kind of say passive-aggressive comments
to him, and, like, to him or about him in meetings that we were having. I would, like, go and, like,
tell somebody else, like, man, you see what that decision that guy made, like, it's a stupid
decision, like, I would, and I would do everything but directly confront the issue, and in doing
that, eventually, somebody came to me and said, Pete, what are you doing? What's wrong? And I had
to realize this sin in my heart that I somehow thought I was better than. I somehow thought
that this other person was so much worse than me. And instead of dealing with that in a way, like,
lavished with the grace of God like we can do, instead, I was doing that passive aggressively,
critically, condemning him, tearing him down. I was doing all that stuff. And it wasn't until a
brother came along and confronted me and said, Pete, what you're doing is not right. This is not
how you live in the grace and mercy of God. And he challenged me, and I realized I had to go to that
brother. I had to confess to him. I had to say, hey, I apologize. I've been critical and judgmental
toward you. Will you forgive me? And you know what? That brother forgave me. We were to love each
other, care for each other, be friends with each other, because the grace of God covered that. I
I had to learn that the hard way.
My fear is that we can come here,
we can do the things we do on Sunday
in our life groups, all that.
We can serve, we can do all the stuff that we do.
And behind the scenes,
where we're actually living our relationship
with God and others is just rotten with sin.
So how do you deal with that?
And by the way, I just want to give an invitation here today.
There are some of you,
maybe you are checking out the Christian faith.
Maybe you know the weight
of trying to deal with your own sin
and maybe you've known it for a long time.
You've been trying to hide.
You've been trying to pay the price yourself.
I'm trying to pretend it isn't enslaving you
when you really know that it is.
Can I invite you today to be in Christ with us?
It's not that this is a perfect community,
but we follow a Savior who has given his life for us.
He shed his blood on the cross,
not just for the person sitting next to you, but for you.
And today I want you to be in Christ,
meaning that you trust his sacrifice for you,
that through the blood he shed on the cross,
he has set you free from slavery
and he's set you free from guilt.
It's atoned for.
Can you pray to him today?
Trust in him today.
Say, I'm placing my faith in Jesus as my savior today.
I wanna follow him and live in his grace today.
I would love for you to do that
even on your own now in your relationship with God,
but maybe come and talk to one of the prayer team afterward
and say, hey, I'm choosing to place my faith in Jesus today.
I wanna give you that invitation this morning.
As we want to live in that together,
can I also ask you, are you living in unity with your brothers and sisters in Christ?
Are you living in unity? Where have things like unforgiveness, comparison, gossip, jealousy,
simple personality differences, where have these caused division among us? And is there maybe a
conflict or a conversation you've been avoiding rather than trusting God to redeem and restore?
And lastly, thirdly, do you trust God to work out his purpose and plan?
This is kind of getting back to the mystery stuff
I shared earlier.
A lot of us, we struggle to really follow and trust God
because we're like, God, it doesn't make sense to me.
I don't see the whole roadmap yet.
Again, I've talked before, God doesn't give you a roadmap,
God gives you a compass.
We're like, God, I just can't follow you yet.
I can't fully trust because I don't know everything.
Can I ask you today, can you trust that God has a purpose?
God has a plan.
It's a plan bigger than you or I could possibly conceive of
because it's been from before time until the end of time,
but his plan will be accomplished
through his son, Jesus Christ.
Can we believe that today?
Because when we trust that plan,
then we can actually rest
and have peace in our hearts
even when we don't fully understand.
And if we trust in that plan,
then we can actually take steps of faith
in response to God.
And even when we can't fully control everything,
but we can respond to God and say,
God, I'm gonna take a step of faith today.
And a lot of times we think, oh, it's a step of faith.
Yeah, that's serving God in some way.
That's going on missions.
Maybe that step of faith today
is simply confessing your sin to God.
Saying, God, I can't fix this.
Maybe that step of faith today is
I need to reach out to my sister
because I need to confess something to her.
Maybe that step of faith is
I need to place my faith in Jesus for the first time
even though I can't fully understand.
Can we trust that God's plans are better than ours
and then live in that truth together?
Let's spend some time in response today.
Can I invite us to stand together?
As we're standing here, again, I want to just kind of create some space here
for us personally to respond to God first.
So just kind of bow your head with me,
and maybe you want to just reflect through some of those questions I just asked you.
How am I dealing with the problem of sin?
Am I living in unity?
God wants to unite everything in heaven and earth.
all those warring nations,
all those tribes that hate one another,
all those divided relationships,
everything he wants to bring together in Christ,
am I simply living in unity with my brothers and sisters?
Am I trusting that God's plans are better than mine?
Maybe you want to sit with those questions here
for a moment before God.
And as we have this time to respond,
just as I've shared before,
we really want this to be like,
we must seek intimacy with God.
we must seek fellowship with him
have the hard conversation
rest in the truth
rejoice in the promises
fulfilled in Christ
celebrate his
faithfulness
mourn the things that have been lost
be honest
about the pain
be honest about the confusion
bring that to God
and in relationship with him in this space
let's believe that he is calling us
to that higher calling that starts with deep relationship and fellowship with him.
I'm going to just pray for that for us here for a moment.
After I pray, we'll just kind of have a short open time just for you to pray and seek the
Lord, and then the worship team is going to lead us in a couple songs, and let's let
this be a space to respond to God, to seek him, to say, God, I need to know you.
I must know you more.
God, we invite you here again.
Come, Holy Spirit, work in each and every heart.
give us the gift of faith and trust
set us free in this moment
the power of the blood of Jesus Christ
sanctify us through and through
set us free from the things that have been enslaving us
and bonding us
wash us clean God of all the guilt and all the shame
invite us into your great plan
to know that our lives have a purpose
to be part of what you're doing until the end of time
invite us into that Lord
and especially draw us near Lord
that we would be close to you
that we would know you more
that we would know you so personally
and intimately in this moment Lord
come and speak and move
have your way in us in this space
in Jesus name
let's seek him together
let's respond together